// Reference: The sources of the questions and answers are from the following websites:
// https://testbook.com/objective-questions/mcq-on-conservation-status--621f82b00d3ea551f10485a1
// https://testbook.com/objective-questions/mcq-on-conservation-effort--621f82b7d94aa937799c96b2
// https://testbook.com/objective-questions/mcq-on-ex-situ-conservation--621f8299d94aa937799c9515
// https://testbook.com/objective-questions/mcq-on-in-situ-conservation--621f82720d3ea551f1047eec

export const quizzes = [
    { 
        question: "A taxon which is facing an extremely high risk of extinction in the wild in immediate future is known as", 
        options: ["Critically Endangered", "Exotic", "Vulnerable", "Rare"], 
        answer: 0, 
        hint: "Conservation Status: \n (1) Critically Endangered \n • A species facing an extremely high risk of extinction in the wild is known as critically endangered. \n • Example: Black rhino, Red wolf, Northern white rhino, etc. \n (2) Endangered \n • Species face a very high risk of extinction in the wild known as endangered. \n • Example: Asian elephants, Blue whales, Green sea turtles, etc. \n (3) Vulnerable \n • Species that face a high risk of extinction in the wild are known as vulnerable. \n • Example: Blackbuck, Blue sheep, etc. \n (4) Rare \n • Species that are uncommon, scarce, or infrequently encountered are labelled as rare. \n • Example: Himalayan brown bear, etc. \n (5) Exotic \n • Species of plants and animals that are non-native i.e. an area where they do not occur naturally but are introduced into the system from outside are exotic. \n • Example: Nilgiri tahr etc."
    },
    { 
        question: "The term alpha diversity refers to", 
        options: ["Genetic diversity", "Community and ecosystem diversity", "Species diversity", "More than one of the above"], 
        answer: 2, 
        hint: "Biodiversity can be discussed at three levels: \n • Genetic diversity: refers to the variation of genes within species. \n • Species diversity: refers to the variety of species. It relates to the number of species in a defined area. \n • Ecosystem diversity: refers to differences between ecosystem types and the diversity of habitats and ecological processes occurring within each ecosystem. \n \n Alpha diversity (α-diversity) is defined as the mean diversity of species in different sites or habitats on a local scale."
    },
    { 
        question: "Red Data Book keeps a record of", 
        options: ["Red flowered plant", "All plant and animals present on the earth", "Endangered plants and animals", "All animals present on the earth"], 
        answer: 2, 
        hint: "The Red Data Book, often referred to as the Red List, is the sourcebook which keeps a record of all the endangered animals and plants. This book is maintained by the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN). This book aims to highlight species that are facing a high risk of global extinction, providing valuable data on the trends in species conservation status over time. This helps guide conservation efforts and policies globally to protect these species and their habitats."
    },
    { 
        question: "Endemic species are", 
        options: ["Rare species", "Endangered species", "Imported species", "Species found in a particular area"], 
        answer: 3, 
        hint: "Endemic species are those species of plants and animals which are found exclusively in a particular area. They are not naturally found anywhere else. A particular type of animal or plant may be endemic to a zone, a state or a country. The destruction of their habitat, increasing population and introduction of new species may affect the natural habitat of endemic species and endanger their existence. \n \n Examples of endemic species are: \n Wild Mango endemic flora of the Pachmarhi Biosphere Reserve. \n Bison, Indian giant squirrel and flying squirrel are endemic fauna of this area."
    },
    { 
        question: "_______ radiation may be one reason why the house sparrow is disappearing.", 
        options: ["X-ray", "Cosmic rays", "Cell phone", "Ultra violet rays"], 
        answer: 2, 
        hint: "A few years back the population of sparrow birds started to decline and they were not seen that commonly. They are known to be sensitive to magnetic radiation. An increasing number of cell phone towers in cities apparently are bringing down their populations. The microwaves (300 MHz to 300 GHz) emitted by cell phone towers and handsets have been found to be responsible for damaging the eggs and embryos of sparrows. Several countries have observed a reduction in bird diversity coinciding with the increase in Cellular Mobile Base stations. Pollution has also greatly affected the sparrow population in urban areas."
    },
    { 
        question: "Conservation of biodiversity is important for", 
        options: ["Animals", "Plants", "Animals and plants", "All organisms"], 
        answer: 3, 
        hint: "Conservation of biodiversity implies sustaining the diversity in the ecosystem. \n Some of the factors affecting biodiversity are: \n (1) pollution, \n (2) natural calamities, \n (3) hunting, \n (4) poaching, \n (5) illegal trade, \n (6) overexploitation, \n (7) large scale destruction of forest land for urbanization, etc. \n \n Conservation of biodiversity is protection, upliftment and scientific management of biodiversity so as to maintain it at its threshold level and derive sustainable benefits for the present and future generation. Since every life form on Earth is part of biodiversity, its conservation is also important for every life form on earth."

    },
    { 
        question: "Which of the following birds is a critically endangered species?", 
        options: ["Great Indian Bustard", "Cuckoo", "Peacock", "More than one of the above"], 
        answer: 0, 
        hint: "The Great Indian Bustard (GIB), the State bird of Rajasthan. It is considered India’s most critically endangered bird. It is considered the flagship grassland species, representing the health of the grassland ecology. Its population is confined mostly to Rajasthan and Gujarat. The bird is under constant threats due to collision/electrocution with power transmission lines, hunting (still prevalent in Pakistan), habitat loss and alteration as a result of widespread agricultural expansion, etc."
    },
    { 
        question: "Genetic diversity in agricultural crops is threatened by", 
        options: ["Introduction of high-yielding varieties", "Intensive use of fertilizers", "Extensive intercropping", "More than one of the above"], 
        answer: 0, 
        hint: "To protect potentially critical features that could be utilised to combat an unanticipated future pest or adapt to the needs of the world's food supply, genetic diversity is required in agriculture. \n \n Introduction of high-yielding varieties of seeds: \n High Yielding Variety Seeds (HYV seeds) have a high-yielding capability and are resistant to insects and illnesses. These seeds are of higher grade and are a superior choice for plentiful and healthy crop output. The introduction of high-producing variants causes the rest of the species to be eliminated or cultivated to a minimum. The high-yielding variety subsequently takes over through pollination and other cultivation processes. As a result of the dominance of high-producing varieties, genetic diversity cannot be recognised."
    },
    { 
        question: "Loktak lake is the only place for which kind of endangered deers?", 
        options: ["Chital", "Barasingha", "Sambar", "Sangai"], 
        answer: 3, 
        hint: "The brow-antlered deer is found in Keibul Lamjao National Park in Manipur. It is largely seen over the floating biomass, locally called “phumdi” in the South-Eastern part of Loktak Lake inside the park."
    },
    { 
        question: "How can viable material of endangered species be conserved?", 
        options: ["Gene bank", "Gene pool", "Herbarium", "More than one of the above"], 
        answer: 0, 
        hint: "Conserving viable genetic material of endangered species is crucial for the preservation of biodiversity and the potential future reintroduction or restoration of populations. One method of doing so is through Gene banking. \n \n Gene banking, also known as cryobanking or genetic banking, involves the collection, preservation, and storage of genetic material from endangered species to ensure the conservation of their genetic diversity."
    },
    { 
        question: "Which of the following would you cite as an example of ex-situ conservation being a teacher of Environmental Studies?", 
        options: ["Zoo", "National Park", "Sanctuary", "Biosphere Reserve"], 
        answer: 0, 
        hint: "Ex-situ conservation refers to preserving all live species in artificial or artistic environments that closely resemble their native habitats. It is off-site conservation. It relates to artificial ecosystems. Examples: Zoos, Cryopreservation DNA banks, Aquariums etc."
    },
    { 
        question: "Which one of the following is not a protected area?", 
        options: ["Wildlife Sanctuary", "Zoological Park", "National Park", "Biosphere Reserve"], 
        answer: 1, 
        hint: "Protected area: \n To protect our flora and fauna and their habitats, protected areas called wildlife sanctuaries, national parks and biosphere reserves have been earmarked. Plantation, cultivation, grazing, felling trees, hunting and poaching are prohibited there. \n \n Zoological Park: \n A zoological park is defined as a place in which various animals are kept within enclosures, demonstrated to the public, and can be used for study. Wild animals are kept under human supervision in zoological parks. Animals receive appropriate care, food, and vaccinations. It is ex-situ conservation. For example, Alipore zoological gardens, Kolkata."
    },
    { 
        question: "Biodiversity Hotspots are characterized on the basis of", 
        options: ["Endemic plant and threat perception", "Species of flowering plants", "Endemic flowering plant", "More than one of the above"], 
        answer: 0, 
        hint: "A biodiversity hotspot is a biogeographic region with significant levels of biodiversity that is threatened by human habitation. Biodiversity hotspots have a high concentration of endemic species."
    }
];
